早晨 大家好
記不記得我們學到什麼?
這個教會是怎樣的?
是不是一個很好的教會?
誰覺得這個第一基督教是一個很好的教會?
舉手
有沒有人覺得這個教會有很多問題?
OK 很多問題
有什麼問題?
考考你
記不記得?
有沒有人記得?
有沒有人記得有什麼問題?
上個星期 卡爾蒙大律師就說
我跟這個牧師
好像在explorer
我想跟卡爾蒙大律師
我想跟Sam
我想跟Johnny大律師
我想跟Winnie大律師
是不是這樣?
我不讀Christ Corinthians
Winnie想讀2nd Corinthians
是不是?
Carmen想讀Colossians
每個人都很混亂
所以教會有沒有一個完美的教會?
有沒有?
No perfect church
他有一個saying
如果有一個完美的教會
你一進去
就會變成什麼?
Imperfect church
你一進去就會變成imperfect church
有人呢
就有什麼?
有罪
就有問題
是不是?
所以教會不是一個perfect place
教會是一個什麼?
好像一個什麼?
What is it like?
好像什麼?
好像一個醫院
Everybody needs help
The church is like a hospital
Everybody needs a savior
每個人都要有一個救主
誰是我們的救主?
耶穌是我們的救主
Ok
這個Corinthian church呢
是有什麼問題?
記不記得?
首先呢
Let's go next slide
他們想
他們覺得他們有很多什麼?
有很多worldly wisdom
智慧
世界的智慧
所以呢
他們
保羅就寫信給他們
你不是單單應該有世界的智慧
你需要有屬靈的智慧
Spiritual wisdom
還有呢
他們有opposition to Paul's leadership
他們覺得
哇! 保羅你的leadership style
太謙卑了
我們不想那麼謙卑
我們想很prideful那些
很高級那些
是不是?
想很high class的
我們suffer呢
我們想在那些Hong Kong football club
去suffer
是不是?
我們suffer呢
我們去那些art club去suffer
是不是?
我們吃了很多pizza
好熱氣
This is my kind of suffering
這是first Corinthians的kind of suffering
不是去很遠的地方
去third world country
去吃一些很難吃的東西
去suffer
No! 我們去那些art club去suffer就好了
是不是?
That is the kind of suffering
所以我們看看next slide
保羅就remind他們
是不是?
不單止有worldly wisdom
不單止做一個vibe christian
我們做什麼?
Spiritual christian
是不是?
我們是governed by the holy spirit
Not governed by our feelings
這個燈太舒服了
所以我來崇拜
這個燈太光了
我不來崇拜
是不是?
你是不是一個vibe christian?
Or you are worldly christian
有什麼去satisfy我呢
我就doom scroll到沒眼睛看
才去become a christian
next slide
The chaos within the church
是不是?
剛才我們的mentor就說
I follow Carmen
I follow Winnie
I follow Pastor Johnny
是不是?
上個禮拜保羅就remind我們
我們不單止follow一個人
我們最重要是follow誰?
Follow耶穌
Follow Jesus
And Jesus died for us
And we are his temple
next slide
Our body is the temple of God
上個禮拜Pastor Carmen
remind了我們
好 今個禮拜我們就看chapter 4
Let's read together chapter 4
OK
Let's read together
1,2,3
This then is how you ought to regard us
(......)
Now it is required
that those who have been given a trust
must prove faithful
I care very little
if I am judged by you
or by any human court
Indeed, I do not even judge myself
My conscience is clear
but that does not make me innocent
(......)
At that time, each of you receive that praise from God
OK 好
首先呢
保羅呢
就係講緊咩嘢呀?
佢個apostleship
中文係咩呀?
apostleship
個word apostleship係點解呀?
有冇人知?
耶穌呢有幾多個門徒呀?
12個門徒
門徒係咩嘢嚟㗎?
門徒係咩嘢呀?
Follower of Christ
Right?
Disciple 姐係
佢學耶穌講嗰啲嘢
做嗰啲嘢
佢follow 耶穌
OK
咁如果門徒係
Follower of Christ
咁apostleship 知唔知係咩呀?
邊個係apostleship呀?
保羅係一個apostleship
保羅係做咩㗎?
佢去旅行係咪?
成日去旅行
係mission trip
唔係淨係旅行
Apo means to send off
to send away
係咪?
所以呢apostleship呢
係the one who is sent off
the one who is sent off
所以保羅係畀神send到去邊度呀?
send去邊度呀?
知唔知?
Modern day
佢send咗去邊度?
佢係以色列開始啦
跟住in Damascus
which is modern day
Modern day
Syria
No not Syria
Lebanon right?
Lebanon 係咪?
佢Lebanon嗰度
send咗住on the road to Damascus
睇到好光嘅
你係邊個呀?
點解你persecute我?
我係耶穌 係咪?
And then Jesus sent him where?
去Asia Minor
To Turkey
Corinth is in modern day
知唔知係邊度?
Greece 係咪?
我哋要下個禮拜show個geography map俾你哋
So apostle is one who is been sent off
佢點解去be sent off?
to do what?
去做咩呀?
點解神send佢去邊呀?
去呢啲地方去做咩呀?
去share the gospel
to share the gospel
So today are we apostles?
Are we apostles?
而家我哋係咪apostle?
神差遣我哋係咪apostle?
佢send我哋去邊度呀?
我哋係咪門徒?
神嘅門徒 我哋係咪神嘅門徒?
Yes we are God's disciples
我哋follow耶穌嘅example
We want to become more like Jesus
But God also wants us to become apostles
He wants to send us to our schools
He wants to send us to our work
有冇人返暑期工㗎?
God might be sending
你做咩呀? Ben 做咩呀?
Consulting 你consult 啲咩呀?
打機點打呀?
打機? No? 差唔多
點讀書? 係咪consult人點讀書?
呢個叫tutoring right?
Ok Lucas呢? 有咩暑期工呀你?
Civil engineering? Oh very good
Very good
God wants to send us to our families
今日係咩節呀?
母親節 你有冇寫個card俾你呀媽?
或者send一個very loving message
或者make me do a reel for your mom
有冇做過reel?
Wilson you gonna do a reel for your mom?
No?
Wilson is not here
呢個係Nixon
Nixon係做緊reel係個gathering嗰度
For his mom right?
Nixon同Wilson做個reel for your mom
No? Maybe?
你今日係個group嗰度呢
You do a reel for your mom
想唔想呀?
College group 想唔想呀?
No? 太cringe 呀?
你個媽唔明白呢啲reel係做咩
佢覺得你哋教會做緊啲咩
Ok
God wants to send you to different places
to share the gospel
Whether it's your school, your work, your family
Or maybe you wanna be sent to Taiwan
呢個係個plug for Taiwan mission trip
我哋今個暑假呢
我哋會去台灣Taipei
去做咩呢?
我哋會host一個camp
一個interest camp
可能教英文
教唔同嘅樂器
教唔同嘅interest
去用呢個方法呢
去share God's love
and share our story with the students there
Maybe God is sending you to Taiwan with us this summer
你可以考慮下
Ok
咁今日呢
我哋會睇true apostleship
True apostleship呢
係好多嘢嘅
我哋睇
Servants, stewards, seeing God's judgment
Simple and humble
Suffers and sacrifices
and is a spiritual mentor
一個true apostleship呢
係要有呢啲quality嘅
第一呢
我哋睇
係servant
Ok
We read again
As servants of Christ and those entrusted with the mysteries of God
that God has revealed
Ok
首先呢
一個真正嘅apostle係點㗎?
佢係僕人嚟嘅
He is a servant
僕人係咩呀?
僕人係follow the instructions of God
好似我哋
有冇餐廳㗎?
有冇人去過餐廳㗎?
係咪?餐廳
Ok
好似你餐廳咁樣
係有一個係坐喺前面嘅
有一個呢係坐喺後面嘅
前面嗰個係點㗎?
前面嗰個應該係點㗎?
有冇人去過kayak?
Anybody been kayaking before?
Ok
前面嗰個係點㗎?
你唔記得咗?
你唔係考咗牌㗎咩?
Elias
我一個人㗎
Ok 如果有兩個人呢?
你imagine 呀
前面嗰個人你覺得係會點㗎?
前面嗰個控制方向?
係後面嗰個控制方向
Ok
如果你坐喺後面呢
You control
You are supposed to control the direction
Ok
同埋呢前面嗰個呢係就咁kayak嘅
It just goes with the flow
係咪?
後面嗰個要點呀?
You coordinate with the front and front
同埋呢要係direct the boat
所以呢做servant係應該係後面定係前面嗰個呀?
諗下
諗一次
前面定後面嗰個?
你做僕人呢
係應該係後面choose the direction
嗰個一定係前面嗰個
前面嗰個
係咪?
你就咁跟隨神
神叫你去邊你就去邊
神叫你做咩就講
你做咩
神叫你傳福音同邊個你就傳福音同邊個
係咪?
You are the one in front
Jesus is the one sitting in the back
And you are trusting in him and his direction
Remember that the next time you kayak
You are trusting in Jesus
唔單止係做僕人
We follow God's example
仲有the next word is steward
steward係咩嚟㗎?
知唔知?
有人知steward係咩?
steward
有人知
中文中文係咩話?
Ok
What does it mean?
It means you have been entrusted with something
steward係you've been entrusted with something
And now you are responsible
有冇人屋企有個pet㗎?
有冇人有個pet?
你有咩呀? Jake 有咩呀?
A dog
Have you ever been entrusted with walking the dog?
By yourself?
Yes
咁你出去walk個dog呢
有冇責任呀?
有責任喎
有時啲狗會驚就會走嚟走去
Has your dog ever run away?
No, he haven't
Uncle Vincent有個dog
佢啱啱好conveniently stepped out
佢有隻狗好驚
佢好驚啲truck或者啲bus
所以一出去嗰時
佢就
跟住一睇到啲嘢
咁你拉住佢
有幾次我同Uncle Vincent同Uncle Agnes
個狗驚到走咗
你imagine Uncle Vincent running for his life
Can you imagine Uncle Vincent running for his life
佢催個狗
I've never seen Uncle Vincent run so fast
Never seen him
如果你阿爸你阿媽叫你出去
自己一個walk the dog
You are responsible
You are the steward
to taking care of your dog
所以保羅
Apostle係要點呀?
佢係steward
佢係responsible
responsible for what?
responsible to carry the message of God to others
So stewards need to be responsible
They need to be accountable
你返到屋企呢
你阿爸阿媽睇到個狗
冇咗嘅
或者好污糟嘅
佢就會accountable
What happened Jake to the dog?
What happened?
But Jake is very responsible
Because he is also very faithful
一個very faithful dog carer
所以第一呢就係要做僕人
第二呢就係要做一個steward
What has God entrusted you with?
Maybe God has entrusted you with friends
that you can share the gospel with
Maybe God has entrusted you with gifts
有咩gifts呀你哋?
Gifts to serve the Lord
可能你神叫你嚟台灣去
Start baking
And you teach other kids to bake
Or teach other kids math
Maybe God has entrusted you with math or art
And you can teach art to the students
What has God entrusted you with?
我哋繼續睇next verse
In verse 3 it says
I care very little how I am judged by you
I do not even judge myself
Therefore I judge nothing before the appointed time
I wait until the Lord comes
保羅講咩呀呢度?
點解佢話I don't care
你judge我唔緊要
我judge你我都唔想嘅
最緊要係神點睇我哋
The next slide
第三個S呢
We need to see with God's vision
真正嘅apostle呢
唔係就咁你著衫唔得呀
你好chopped呀
chop來chop去好chop呀
唔係成日咁樣judge人嘅
True apostle呢
係用神個眼去睇人嘅
明唔明呀
唔係你係咁呀咁呀
唔係係用神個眼去睇人
God loves this person
God wants this person to know him
God wants to help him
我哋真正嘅apostleship呢
係要用神個眼去愛人
愛神明唔明白
True apostleship sees with God's vision
It judges only according to the right word
to the word and with the right motive
如果我哋judge呢
我哋係用神嘅話語去instruct人嘅
明唔明白
我哋係用神嘅motive
the right motive
去幫人去愛人去judge
So the third thing is we see with God's vision
We only judge according to God's word
Ok
God says this is wrong
And that is why I am trying to instruct you
To help you to walk according to God's word
Ok now is the time for discussion
Two questions number one
To what extent are you willing to serve Jesus
準備呀
Ok
What things do you find hard to say yes to
你想唔想做神嘅僕人
如果你想呢
有咩你覺得好難say yes嘅
Ok
第二個question
As a steward of Jesus
What has God placed in your life to be responsible for
神畀咗你咩係be responsible
To be responsible for
Ok let's go into groups
Ok 有冇人想分享
你哋覺得咩係好難say yes to Jesus嘅
如果神叫你做佢嘅僕人有冇呀
To a large extent 好多嘢都
Ok 例如呢
Give me one example
One example
Temptations my phone
第二啲呢
第二啲有冇人想分享
可能姐係like probably ECAs
Or like big commitments
In my schedule right
What
Extracurriculars
No it's hard to say like yes to sacrifice them
Or like to put them down
For like Jesus
So like yeah
有冇人覺得好似Jedah咁樣嘅
如果耶穌叫你
放低個doom scrolling嘅
覺得好難嘅
Volleyball ok
頭先講咗一個記號嘅
就係例如你要去
即係唔知係咪應該幫一個
喺個班好唔受歡迎
Someone who is really not popular in the class
你要同佢玩
但如果你同佢玩呢
你又會畀你同學話
你做乜同個unpopular嘅人玩
係啦 it's hard
So associating with people that are less popular
邊個覺得好難嘅
如果耶穌叫你做
Ok
All right
係囉 放棄排球
我放棄乒乓球
我哋答第一題嘅
咁但係我哋又define咗少少嘢
即係問我哋
即係要想去服侍耶穌嘅時候
有一次我哋問
咩叫服侍耶穌呢
你覺得咩係服侍耶穌呀
你啱啱答
Follow the rules
Go to church
全服一去
咁好難就係邊
Follow the rules
Follow the rules 係好難嘅
Ok 第二個問題呢
What has God given you to be a steward of
有冇人
College group 有冇呀
有冇人分享
College group 有冇人分享
Second question
My dog
Ok
身邊嘅人
所有身邊嘅人
家人朋友同學都係神entrust俾我哋
有人話
我哋自己嘅身體呢
都係神entrust俾我哋
要照顧好自己嘅身體
先可以侍奉神
That's true
If you don't have a healthy body
You can't serve Jesus right
You are sick all the time
你點幫人呢係咪
如果你sick all the time
第四樣嘢呢
To be a true apostle
We need to be simple and humble
保羅呢就話
Do not be puffed up
係咪
唔好覺得你
嘩 你好勁呀
你識好多嘢呀
係咪
Corinthian church就係咁樣啦
佢覺得佢好
佢覺得自己好spiritual
嘩 spiritual pride
嘩 你睇下我
我返教會
好準時嘅
嘩 我敬拜呢係raise my hand嘅
嘩 我唔玩手機嘅
我好聽個mentor講嘅
係咪
我有spiritual pride
I am better than others
As a Christian
咁所以保羅呢就話
True apostle
係simple and humble
係咪
點解你咁puffed up呢
佢個word係puffed up
點解你look down on人哋呢
你嗰啲gift呢
係邊個畀你嘅呢
啲gift係邊個畀你嘅
Who gives you your gifts
Your talents
God gives you your talents
你啲material things
你有咁多clothes
係邊個畀錢你買㗎
邊個畀錢你買㗎
Who gives you the money
Who provides you all things
Ultimately it is God
咁點解你驕傲呢
It is God who gives you everything
You should not be puffed up
Why boast
所以呢個係保羅嘅example
The next thing as an apostle
係佢係要咩
Suffer and sacrifice
佢話apostles are what
They are those who suffer
呢個係一個Roman procession嚟㗎
知唔知Roman procession係咩
即係let's say Caesar
He wins the war
跟住佢返嚟Rome嗰時呢
佢有一個line up嘅係咪
佢有一個procession
Assembly
咁你覺得佢會擺咩先㗎
佢擺邊個先㗎
Who usually comes first in the procession
Anybody knows
Usually the generals or the army people
The ones who won you the victory
They will step up first
跟住可能Caesar
跟住最尾嗰啲人係邊個嚟㗎
Procession最尾嗰啲人係咩嚟㗎
邊個嚟㗎
煮飯嗰啲
煮飯
The chefs
最尾嗰啲係多數嗰啲enemies
That you have captured
So the warriors go first
And then Caesar goes
And then those
The spews of war
What's the word
The victories of war
Those you have beaten
Those you have conquered
You march them on to humiliate them
So Paul is saying
The apostles are not ones who are the victorious ones
That stand in the front
They are the ones in the end
They suffer
They are displayed at the end of processions
They are condemned to die in arenas
And they are a spectacle to the whole world
保羅真係講咩呀
如果你做真正嘅apostle呢
係要受苦嘅
Who are you suffering for
Suffering for Jesus
You are suffering for Jesus
Let's go to the comparison
False apostleship
You have all you want
You are rich, you reign
You look wise
True apostleship
You are hungry and thirsty
有時你傳福音嗰時
你畀人猜遣去唔同嘅地方
Sometimes you are hungry
And you are thirsty for the Lord
Sometimes you are poorly dressed and buffeted
Sometimes you are homeless
有時保羅猜遣去唔同嘅地方
佢有冇屋企住呀
佢冇喎
He might be living on the street
He might be living in tents
Or somebody's house
It is tough
He is a fool to the world
And a scum to the world
有啲人係唔睇起佢
你傳福音
啲人去believe in the Roman gods
They look down on the Christians
啲Christian冇嘢做嘅
唔畀公佢做嘅
因為佢唔係believe in the Roman gods
They were looked down on
And so true apostles
Suffer for the Lord
They suffer for the Lord
Ok, the last thing is
True apostles
Ok, let's look at the next slide
Problems within the Corinthian church
我哋加咗兩個今日
仲有佢哋係有spiritual pride
They thought they were better than everybody else
They knew more than everybody else
They thought they had more than everybody else
That they were rich, they were reigning
That they looked wise
They had all they wanted
仲有佢embarrassed of Paul's suffering
And humble state
保羅有好多時
佢俾人掉咗去坐監
Corinthian church覺得好醜
你又俾人throw into jail
你又冇屋企
又好似好醜
They were embarrassed by Paul
你周圍走去傳福音
又冇乜錢
We are kind of embarrassed by you
你個reputation is not the greatest
amongst the foreigners
So this was the problem in the Corinthian church
The last thing that Paul says is this
I am writing this not to shame you
Let's go to the next verse
But to warn you as my dear children
Even if you have thousand guardians in Christ
You do not have many fathers
For in Christ Jesus
I became your father through the gospel
Therefore I urge you to imitate me
保羅寫呢個信俾Corinthian church
It's to remind them
These are the things that you need to change
He's instructing them
You need to change these things
And most importantly
I am here for you as a spiritual father
He says this
You do not have many fathers
But for in Christ I became your spiritual father
Through the gospel
Therefore I urge you to imitate me
保羅呢係一個spiritual father
To the Corinthian church
And as an apostle
We need to be spiritual mentors to somebody
係咪 你有冇諗過
You are a spiritual mentor to somebody
可能未諗過係咪
I am young
Who wants to follow me right
Nobody right
I am so young
I am still learning
但係保羅係話
A true apostle is a spiritual mentor
You can be a spiritual mentor
To those around you
Ok let's invite Martin to come up
Let's give a hand to Martin
Ok Martin how long have you been in church now
I've been in this church for about 6 or 7 years
你覺得你首先返嚟教會嗰時
你覺得係點呀
I thought that I was like going along
With my parents just to come and play
And didn't take like
God or sermons very seriously
Yeah that's true
So what changed
What changed
What started to change in your life
When did you start to take God more seriously
So when I was 7
I went swimming with my sister and my mom
And my dad was out of town
And then I was the only one
To go to the male changing room
And I wanted to go to the toilet
So I went to the stall
And then I locked the door
And after I finished going
I couldn't unlock the door
As the lock was budged
And then I kept screaming help help
But no one listened
So you were trapped inside the washroom
Yeah I was trapped inside
You couldn't crawl under or anything
No the door was too tall
Ok and how long do you think you were trapped for
I was screaming help for at least 2 minutes
2 minutes ok
Anyone was trapped in the toilet
Anybody
What happened
I was trapped in a plane
Oh you were in a plane
Oh no
The doors were this way
So one of the doors had the back door open
And I couldn't reach the other side
So you were trapped for how long
Uncle Vincent
I was trapped for like 5 minutes
Oh 5 minutes ok
Screaming
好像Martin那樣
Yeah
Martin was screaming
Ok what happened afterwards
And then after that
I was having a panic attack
So I did the only thing that I could do
Which was to pray
So I broke down on my knees
And I prayed to God
And then after that
After the prayer
He actually calmed me down
And the first time I tried
I could unlock the door
After that
Ok
And that was when I personally experienced God
And I actually knew that
God was real
He was alive
He was with me
Very good
And so
Now that you've become Christian
How do you think God has affected your life
Or how is He a part of your life
So He has actually
Done a lot of miracles in my life
Because even the small ones count
And I think that
Every day I wake up
It's actually already a miracle, a blessing
Because He's given life to all of us
And I think that we should always start our day
By praying to Him
And yeah, worshipping Him
And I think that He has helped me
Because when I'm in fear, when I'm in pain
I can always trust in Him and rely on Him
To give me peace, to give me hope, to give me happiness
Yeah, very good
We're talking about apostleship today
To be sent out to share the gospel
And you have a story about that, right
Yeah, so one of my friends
I met in primary school called Ryan
He was a Catholic
And last year during Easter
I said to him
Why not come to this church to maybe
Experience
Yeah, experience, make some friends
Learn more about God
And I think that during that time
God actually softened his heart
And he actually came along with me
And that's the experience
He really enjoyed it
So I hope that he could come again
Very good
And so he took the courage
To invite his friend, a primary friend
To know God more
And so that's what we want to
We want to do here and explore
Invite our friends
The friends that God has entrusted us with
And bring them to Jesus
So let's give a hand to Martin
For sharing today
Very good
True apostleship
We are servants, we serve, okay
We are stewards
We are faithful
For what God has placed in our life
Maybe it's our talents
Maybe it's our friends
Maybe it's our family
Maybe it's our testimony, right
We are seeing with God's judgment
To encourage others, to instruct others
And we are simple and humble
We set an example, right
That we are humble before the Lord
We persevere through suffering and sacrifice
And we also are spiritual mentors
We lead others towards Jesus
Like Martin led Ryan to our church
To know more about God
And so the last verse, it says this
Next slide
Don't let anyone look down on you
Because you are young
But set an example for the believers
In speech, in conduct, in love, in faith
And in purity
Paul is telling Timothy
As a very young pastor
Don't let anyone look down on you
God can use you for his work
And just as Paul is saying that to Timothy
Paul is saying that to us today
Just because you're in high school
You're in middle school
God can use you
God can use your story
Like God can use Martin
To bring your friends to Jesus
To be a true apostle
Let's pray and we'll end today
Father, we come before you
We thank you that you have called us
All to be your servants
To follow you
To know you
To love you
We also thank you
That you have entrusted us
With our gifts and talents
And most importantly
You've entrusted us with the truth of the gospel
To share the truth with our friends
To share the truth of God's love with our friends
Help us, Lord
To be who you called us to be
To share your light to those around us
As we go into our groups
May you bless our groups
May you bless our mentors
Fill them with the Holy Spirit
That they would lead these groups
According to your spirit
May it be blessed with fruitful conversation
And prayerful consideration
As we encourage one another in these groups
May you be with us
In Christ's name we pray, amen
(字幕由 Amara.org 社群提供)